My name is Emiliano Salinas
إسمي إيمليانوا سلاناس
and I'm going to talk about the role
وسوف اتحدث لكم عن الدور
we members of society play
الذي نلعبه نحن ابناء المجتمع
in the violent atmosphere
في إطار العنف
this country is living in right now.
المستشري في البلد الذي اعيش فيه الآن
I was born in 1976.
لقد ولدت في عام 1976
I grew up in a traditional Mexican family.
وترعرعت في عائلة مكسيكية تقليدية
As a child, I had a pretty normal life:
كطفل .. كانت حياتي اعتيادية جداً
I would go to school, play with my friends and cousins.
كنت اذهب الى المدرسة .. والعب مع اصدقائي وابناء عمومتي
But then my father became President of Mexico
ولكن من ثم غدا والدي رئيس المكسيك
and my life changed.
وتغيرت حياتي تماماً
What I'm about to say,
وما انا بصدد قوله
at least some of what I'm about to say,
او بالاصح ما سيتنسنى لي قوله
will cause controversy.
سوف يسبب جدلاً
Firstly, because I'm the one who's going to say it.
بسبب انه اولاً .. انا الذي سوف اقول هذا الامر
And secondly, because what I'm going to say is true,
والثاني .. هو ان ما سأقوله صحيح تماماً وواقعي
and it will make a lot of people nervous
وسوف يثير حفيظة كثير من الاشخاص
because it's something we don't want to hear.
لانه شيء يصمون آذانهم عنه
But it's imperative that we listen
ولكن من المهم أن نستمع لذلك
because it's undeniable and definitive.
لانه امرٌ واقعي وحقيقي وحتمي يحدث من حولنا
It will also make members of
ان هذا الحديث سوف يعذب ايضاً
criminal organizations nervous
اعضاء المنظمات الاجرامية
for the same reasons.
لعدة أسباب
I'm going to talk about the role
سوف اتحدث عن دور
we members of society play
ابناء المجتمع
in this phenomenon,
في هذه الظاهرة
and about four different response levels
وعن 4 مستويات للرد
we citizens have against violence.
على ظاهرة العنف يمكننا نحن كمواطنين ان نقوم بها
I know many will find it difficult to separate the fact
واعلم ان الكثير سوف يجدون صعوبة
that I'm Carlos Salinas de Gortari's son
في ان يقوموا بتنحية فكرة اني ابن كالرلوس ساليناس دي غورتاري
from the fact that I'm a citizen
عن فكرة كوني اني مواطن
concerned about the country's current situation.
اهتم بوضع بلدي الحالي
Don't worry.
لا تقلقوا ..
It's not necessary for understanding
ليس من الضروري ان تعوا
the importance of what I'm going to say.
اهمية ما اتحدث عنه
I think we have a problem in Mexico.
اعتقد اننا نعاني من مشكلة في المكسيك
We have a big problem.
انها مشكلة كبيرة جداً
I think there's consensus on this.
ولها تبعات كبيرة
No one argues --
لا احد يحاجج في هذا الامر
we all agree there's a problem.
الجميع متفق على انها مشكلة
What we don't agree on
ولكن ما نختلف عليه
is what the problem actually is.
هو تعريف المشكلة تحديداً ومسببها
Is it the Zetas? The drug traffickers? The government?
هل هم جماعة الزيتاس ؟ ام تجار المخدرات ؟ ام الحكومة
Corruption? Poverty? Or is it something else?
ام الشركات ؟ ام الفقر ؟ ام شيء آخر
I think none of these is the problem.
اعتقد ان المشكلة ليس في اي مما سبق
I don't mean they don't deserve attention.
لا اعني ان ما سبق لا يحتاج الاهتمام
But we won't be able to take care of any of those things
ولكن لن نستطيع معالجة كل ما سبق
if we don't solve the real problem
ان لم نحل اولاً مشكلة المكسيك الحقيقية
we have in Mexico first.
التي تستشري في المكسيك
The real problem we have is
ان المشكلة الحقيقية
most of us Mexicans, we believe we are victims
هي ان جميع المكسيكين يؤمنون انهم ضحايا
of our circumstances.
ضحايا الظروف
We are a country of victims.
نحن بلد الضحايا
Historically, we've always acted as victims
تاريخياً .. لقد وصمنا انفسنا بصفة الضحايا وتعاملنا مع انفسنا على هذا النحو
of something or somebody.
سواء كنا ضحية شخص او ظرف
We were victims of the Spaniards.
فنحن ضحايا الاسبان
Then we were victims of the French.
وضحايا الفرنسين
Then we were victims of Don Porfirio.
وضحايا دون بروفيريو
Then we were victims of the PRI.
وضحايا منظمة PRI
Even of Salinas.
وحتى ضحايا سيلاناس "الرئيس "
And of El Peje.
و " إل بيجي " - شخصية عامة -
And now of the Zetas and the traffickers and the criminals and the kidnappers ...
اليوم نعد ضحايا " تجار المخدرات و المجرمين و الزيتاس و .. و ..
Hold on! Wait a minute!
توقفوا قليلاً ..
What if none of these things is the problem?
ليس اي من ذلك المشكلة
The problem is not the things we feel victims of.
المشكلة ليست فيما نظن اننا ضحاياه
The problem is that we play the role of victims.
مشكلة هي اننا نحب لعب دور الضحايا
We need to open our eyes and see that we are not victims.
نحن نحتاج الى ان نوسع افقنا لكي ندرك اننا لسنا ضحايا
If only we stopped feeling like victims,
ان استطعنا ان نتوقف عن النظر الى انفسنا على اننا لسنا ضحايا
if we stopped acting as victims,
سوف نتوقف عن التصرف وكأننا كذلك
our country would change so much!
وسوف تتغير بلدنا كثيراً
I'm going to talk about how to go from a society
سوف اخبركم عن كيفية نقل المجتمع
that acts as a victim of circumstances
من مجتمع يظن نفسه ضحية الظروف
to a responsible, involved society
الى مجتمع مسؤول و منخرط في العمل
that takes the future of its country in its own hands.
ويسعى نحو صناعة المستقبل بملء يديه
I'm going to talk about four different levels
سوف احدثكم عن اربعة مستويات مختلفة
of civil response against violence,
من التجاوب المدني"المجتمعي" ضد العنف
from weakest
من التجاوب الاضعف
to strongest.
نحو الاقوى
The first level, the weakest level of civil response against violence,
ان اول نوع من الاستجابة المدنية تجاه العنف - الاضعف -
is denial and apathy.
هي الانكار واللامبالة
Today, much of Mexican society is in denial
اليوم .. العديد من المكسيكين يعيشون في حالة انكار
of the situation we're going through.
للوضع الذي يعتريهم
We want to go on with our daily life
كل ما يريدونه العيش يوما ب يوم
even though we are not living under normal circumstances.
حتى لو لم تكن ظروف المعيشة تلك ملائمة
Daily life in our country is,
ان الحياة اليومية في بلدنا
to say the least,
اقل ما يقال عنها
under extraordinary, exceptional circumstances.
في ظل ظروف، غير عادية واستثنائية.
It's like someone who has a serious illness
انها مثل شخص يعاني من مرض عضال
and pretends it's the flu
ويدعي انه مصاب بالحمى فحسب
and it will just go away.
وستزول قريباً
We want to pretend that Mexico has the flu.
نحن نريد ان ندعي ان المكسيك مصابة بالحمى
But it doesn't.
ولكن هذا غير صحيح
Mexico has cancer.
المكسيك مصابة بالسرطان
And if we don't do something about it,
وان لم نتصرف حيال هذا
the cancer will end up killing it.
سوف يستشري السرطان ويقتلنا تماماً
We need to move Mexican society
نحن نحتاج ان نحرك المجتمع المكسيكي
from denial and apathy
من الانكار واللامبالة
to the next level of citizen response,
الى المستوى التالي - الاعلى - من الاستجابة المدنية " المجتمعية "
which is, effectively, recognition.
والتي هي الاعتراف والفاعلية
And that recognition will sow fear --
ان الاعتراف سوف يزرع الخوف
recognizing the seriousness of the situation.
اقصد الاعتراف بمدى جدية الموضوع
But, fear is better than apathy
ولكن الخوف افضل من اللامبالة
because fear makes us do something.
لان الخوف يدفعنا للقيام بشيء
Many people in Mexico
العديد من الاشخاص في المكسيك
are afraid today.
خائفون اليوم
We're very afraid.
لقد كنا خائفون كثيراً
And we're acting out of that fear.
ونحن نتصرف بدافع من ذلك الخوف
And let me tell you what the problem is
ودعوني اخبركم ماهية المشكلة
with acting out of fear --
بالتصرف بدافع الخوف
and this is the second level of civil response:
نعم إن المستوى الثاني من الاستجابة المدنية " المجتمعية " تجاه العنف
fear.
هو الخوف
Let's think about Mexican streets:
دعونا نفكر قليلاً فيما يخص الشوارع المكسيكية
they're unsafe because of violence,
انها غير آمنة بسبب العنف
so people stay at home.
الناس تبقى في منازلها
Does that make streets more or less safe?
ولكن هل يجعل هذا الشوارع أكثر أمناً .. ام اقل ؟
Less safe!
أقل !
So streets become more desolate and unsafe,
فما يحدث ان الشوراع تغدو اقل امنا .. واكثر عزلة
so we stay home more --
لذا نحن نبقى في المنازل اكثر
which makes streets even more desolate and unsafe,
فتصبح الشوارع اكثر عزلة واقل امناً
and we stay home even more.
فنرد على ذلك بالبقاء في المنازل اكثر
This vicious circle ends up with the whole population
ان هذه الدائرة من الافعال وردات الفعل تنتهي بجعل المجتمع باكمله
stuck inside their houses, scared to death --
قابع في منزله خائف من الموت
even more afraid than when we were out on the streets.
خائف في منزله اكثر من حاله في الشارع
We need to confront this fear.
علينا ان نواجه هذا الخوف
We need to move Mexican society,
علينا ان نحرك المجتمع المكسيكي
the members of society who are at this level,
علينا ان نرفع الاشخاص الذين يقبعون في
to the next level, which is action.
هذا المستوى - الخوف - الى المستوى التالي - العمل -
We need to face our fears and take back our streets,
علينا ان نواجه الخوف وان نستعيد شوراعنا مرة اخرى
our cities, our neighborhoods.
نستعيد مدننا .. احيائنا
For many people, acting involves courage.
بالنسبة لكثير من الاشخاص .. العمل يعني الغضب
We go from fear to courage.
ان الامر بالنسبة لهم الانتقال من الخوف الى الغضب
They say, "I can't take it anymore.
يقولون " لايمكننا احتمال الامر اكثر من هذا
Let's do something about it."
يجب ان نقوم بامر حياله "
Recently --
مؤخراً
this is a sensitive figure --
وهذا رقم حساس ..
35 public lynchings have been recorded
فقد سجل 35 حالة اعدام " إجرامي " - اعدام المجرمين خارج سلطة القانون -
so far in 2010
عام 2010
in Mexico.
في المكسيك
Usually it's one or two a year.
كان قديما هناك اعدام " إجرامي " او اثنين كل عام
Now we're experiencing one every week.
اليوم يحدث هذا كل اسبوع
This shows that society is desperate
هذا يشير الى ان المجتمع اصيب بالاحباط
and it's taking the law into its own hands.
وبدأ يطبق القانون بيديه
Unfortunately, violent action --
لسوء الحظ العنف كرد فعل
though action is better than no action --
يبدو افضل من اللافعل
but taking part in it
ولكن هذا يوسع
only disguises violence.
دائرة العنف فحسب
If I'm violent with you
ان كنت عنيفاً معك
and you respond with violence,
سوف ترد علي بالعنف أنت أيضاً
you become part of the violence
فستغدو - جزء - من دائرة العنف
and you just disguise my violence.
رغم انك تكره العنف
So civil action
لذا ان التصرف " المجتمعي "
is vital,
محوري
but it's also vital to take people
لذا من المهم
who are at the level of courage
نقل من هم في مستوى الغضب
and violent action
والفعل العنيف
to the next level,
الى المستوى التالي
which is non-violent action.
وهو مستوى لا وجود للعنف فيه
It's pacific, coordinated civil action,
انه الفعل المجتمعي المنظم المحدد
which doesn't mean passive action.
لا يعني فعل سلبي
It means it's determined and effective,
انه يعني إستجابة محددة وفعالة
but not violent.
ولكنه ليس عنف
There are examples of this kind of action in Mexico.
هناك امثلة كثيرة للاستجابات اللاعنفية في المكسيك
Two years ago, in Galena City, Chihuahua,
منذ سنتين في مدينة جالينا , تشيهاها
a member of the community was kidnapped,
خطف شخص من المجتمع
Eric Le Barón.
اسمه إيرك لي بارون
His brothers, Benjamín and Julián,
اخوته .. بيناجمين و جوليان
got together with the rest of the community
اجتمعوا مع افراد من المجتمع
to think of the best course of action:
لكي يتفقوا على اسلوب الرد الامثل
to pay the ransom,
هل يدفعون الفدية
to take up arms and go after the kidnappers
هل يرفعون الاسلحة ويلاحقون المختطفين
or to ask the government for help.
هل يطلبوا من الدولة التدخل
In the end, Benjamín and Julián decided
في النهاية بيناجمين و جوليان قررا
the best thing they could do
ان افضل شيء يمكن القيام به
was to organize the community and act together.
هو ان ينظموا المجتمع ويتصرفوا كيد واحدة
So what did they do?
لكن ماذا فعلوا ؟
They mobilized the whole community of Le Barón
لقد تمركز افراد مجتمع لي بارون
to go to Chihuahua,
في شيهاها
where they organized a sit-in
حيث نظموا اعتصام
in the central park of the city.
في الحديقة العامة للمدينة
They sent a message to the kidnappers:
وارسلوا رسالة الى الخاطفين
"If you want your ransom come and get it.
" ان اردتم فديتكم .. تعالوا وخذوها ..
We'll be waiting for you right here."
نحن هنا ننتظركم "
They stayed there.
لقد اعتصموا هناك
Seven days later, Eric was set free
بعد سبعة أيام .. تم إخلاء سبيل إيريك
and was able to return home.
وعاد إلى منزله
This is an example of what an organized society can do,
هذا نموذج عما يمكن للمجتمع ان يقوم به
a society that acts.
هذا هو الفعل المدني " المجتمعي "
Of course, criminals can respond.
وحتماً المجرمين سوف يتجاوبون معه ..
And in this case, they did.
لقد فعلوا ذلك في تلك الحالة ..
On July 7th, 2009,
في السابع من تموز عام 2009
Benjamín Le Barón was murdered.
تم اغتيال بينجامين لي بارون
But Julián Le Barón keeps working
ولكن جوليان لي بارون استمر بالعمل
and he has been mobilizing communities in Chihuahua
وشرع بدفع المجتمع للاعتصام في شيهاها
for over a year.
لمدة عام
And for over a year he has known that a price has been put on his head.
ولعام كامل .. كان يعرف ان " حياته " في خطر .. وان هناك من قد يدفع لقتله ..
But he keeps fighting.
ولكنه استمر في القتال ..
He keeps organizing.
واستمر في التنظيم
He keeps mobilizing.
واستمر في الاعتصام
These heroic acts are present all over the country.
ان هذه الافعال البطولية اصبحت منتشرة في البلد
With a thousand Juliáns working together,
وبوجود آلاف من أشباه جوليان يعملون سوية
Mexico would be a very different country.
يمكن يصبح لدينا مكسيك جديد
And they're out there!
وهؤلاء موجودون في المجتمع
They just have to raise their hands.
كل ما عليهم القيام به .. هو التحرك والعمل
I was born in Mexico, I grew up in Mexico
لقد ولدت في المكسيك .. ونشأت فيه
and along the way, I learned to love Mexico.
وعلى مدى حياتي .. تعلمت ان احب المكسيك
I think anyone who has stepped foot on this land --
واعتقد ان اي شخص وطأت قدمه هذه الارض
not to mention all Mexican people --
ولا اقصد المكسيكين
will agree that it's not difficult
سوف يوافقني انه ليس من الصعب
to love Mexico.
الوقوع في حب المكسيك
I've traveled a lot
انا اسافر كثيراً
and nowhere else have I found the passion Mexicans have.
ولم اجد شغف مماثل لذلك الذي املكه تجاه المكسيك
That devotion we feel
لم اجد هذا الوله الذي يشعر فيه المكسيكيون تجاه
for the national football team.
فريقهم الوطني لكرة القدم
in helping victims of disasters,
مساعدة المنكوبين في الازمات
such as the earthquake in 1985
كما حدث في زلزال 1985
or this year's floods.
او في سنوات الفيضان
The passion with which we've been singing the national anthem
و الوله الذي يشعر فيه المكسيكيون اثناء انشادهم نشيدهم الوطني
since we were kids.
مذ هم صغارٌ
When we thought Masiosare
نحن يد واحدة عندما نواجه "ماسيوسار" - اسم تراثي -
was the strange enemy,
العدو الغريب
and we sang, with a childlike heart,
نحن ننشد بقلوب وجلة
"a soldier in each son."
كل طفل مكسيكي هو جندي للدفاع ضد العدو
I think the biggest insult,
اعتقد ان اكبر اهانة
the worst way you can offend a Mexican
يمكن ان توجهها الى المكسيكي ..
is to insult their mother.
هي ان تهين والدته
A mother is the most sacred thing in life.
ان الام هي أهم شيء في حياة المكسيكي
Mexico is our mother and today she cries out for her children.
ان المكسيك هي والدتنا جميعاً .. وهي تبكينا على الدوام
We are going through the darkest moment
ونحن نمر اليوم عبر فترة صعبة
in our recent history.
في تاريخ المكسيك الحديث
Our mother, Mexico, is being violated before our very eyes.
ان والدتنا المكسيك .. يتم انتهاكها امام اعيننا
What are we going to do?
ما نحن فاعلين حيال هذا ؟
Masiosare, the strange enemy, is here.
"ماسيوسار" - اسم تراثي - العدو الغريب .. كائنٌ أمامنا
Where is the soldier in each son?
فأين الجندي الذي يكمن في كل طفل ؟
Mahatma Gandhi,
المهاتما غاندي
one of the greatest civil fighters of all time, said,
هو واحد من اعظم المحاربين من اجل الحقوق المدنية قال ذات يوم
"Be the change you wish to see in the world."
" كن التغير الذي تريده في هذا العالم "
Today in Mexico we're asking for Gandhis.
اليوم في المكسيك .. نحن نحتاج لأشخاص مثل غاندي
We need Gandhis.
نحن نحتاجهم
We need men and women who love Mexico
نحن نحتاج رجال ونساء يحبون المكسيك
and who are willing to take action.
وعازمون على العمل من اجله
This is a call for every true Mexican
هذا نداء لكل مكسيكي
to join this initiative.
لكي يشارك بهذه المبادرة
This is a call
هذا نداء
so that every single thing we love about Mexico --
من اجل كل شيء نحبه في المكسيك
the festivals, the markets,
المهرجانات .. المحال
the restaurants, the cantinas,
المطاعم .. المقاصف
the tequila, the mariachis, the serenades,
التكيلا .. الماريشايس .. السيريندايس - رموز مكسيكية -
the posadas, El Grito, the Day of the Dead,
البوسداس .. إل جريتو .. يوم الموتى - رموز مكسيكية -
San Miguel, the joy, the passion for life,
سان ميجيل .. الحب .. السعادة .. الشغف بالحياة
the fight and everything it means to be Mexican --
علينا ان نحارب لكي تبقى المكسيك
doesn't disappear from this world.
لكي تبقى هذه الاشياء التي نحب في هذا العالم
We're facing a very powerful opponent.
نحن نواجه عدو صنديد
But we are many more.
ولكننا الأكثر ..
They can take a man's life.
نعم يمكنهم ان يقتنصوا حياة الفرد
Anyone can kill me,
اي شخص يمكن ان يقتلني ..
or you, or you.
او يقتلك .. او يقتلك ..
But no one can kill
ولكن لا قدرة لأحد على قتل ..
the spirit of true Mexicans.
الروح الحقيقة القابعة في كل مكسيكي
The battle is won,
هذه المعركة .. سنربح بها لامحالة
but we still have to fight it.
ولكننا بحاجة الى القتال
2000 years ago, the Roman poet Juvenal
منذ 2000 عام .. الشاعر الروماني جوفينال
said something that today echoes
قال شيئاً ينطبق على واقعنا
in the heart of every true Mexican.
وله صدى في قلب كل مكسيكي حقيقي
He said, "Count it the greatest sin
قال " إن أعظم خطئية في هذه الحياة
to prefer life to honor,
ان تفضل الحياة على الشرف
and for the sake of living
وان تتنازل عما هو حق لك في حياتك
to lose what makes life worth living."
حرصاُ على حياتك فحسب "
Thank you.
شكراً
(Applause)
(تصفيق)